<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v2004 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by lcollins (Firaxis Games) -->
<!-- Sid Meier's Civilization 4 -->
<!-- Copyright Firaxis Games 2005 -->
<!-- -->
<!-- Game Text - New -->
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_FRANZ</Tag>
		<English>Franz Joseph</English>
		<French>Franz Joseph</French>
		<German>Franz Joseph</German>
		<Italian>Francesco Giuseppe</Italian>
		<Spanish>Franz Joseph</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_FRANZ_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Franz Joseph I[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Emperor of Austria, Apostolic King of Hungary and King of Bohemia[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived: [\BOLD]1848-1916[PARAGRAPH:2:1][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Franz Joseph I (in Hungarian I. Ferenc József, in English Francis Joseph I) (August 18, 1830 – November 21, 1916) of the Habsburg Dynasty was Emperor of Austria, Apostolic King of Hungary, King of Bohemia from 1848 until 1916 and a German prince (Deutscher Fürst). His 68-year reign is the third-longest in the recorded history of Europe (after that of Louis XIV of France and Johannes II, Prince of Liechtenstein). Franz Joseph was born in the Schönbrunn Palace in Vienna, the oldest son of Archduke Franz Karl (the younger son of Emperor Franz), and his wife Princess Sophie of Bavaria. Because his uncle, from 1835 the Emperor Ferdinand, was weak-minded, and his father unambitious and retiring, the young Archduke "Franzl" was brought up by his mother as a future Emperor with emphasis on devoutness, responsibility and diligence. Franzl came to idealize his grandfather, der Gute Kaiser Franz, who had died shortly before his fifth birthday, as the ideal monarch. At the age of 13 young Archduke Franz started a career as a colonel in the Austrian army. From that point onward, his fashion was dictated by army style and for the rest of his life he normally wore the uniform of a junior officer. Franz Joseph was soon joined by three younger brothers - Archduke Ferdinand Maximilian (born 1832, the future Emperor Maximilian of Mexico); Archduke Karl Ludwig (born 1833), and Archduke Ludwig Viktor (born 1842), but a sister, Maria Anna (born 1835), died young, at the age of four. Following the resignation of the Chancellor Prince Metternich during the Revolutions of 1848, the young Archduke, whom it was widely expected would soon succeed his uncle on the throne, was appointed Governor of Bohemia on 6 April, but never took up the post. Instead, Franz was sent to the front in Italy, joining Field Marshal Radetzky on campaign on 29 April, receiving his baptism of fire on 5 May at Santa Lucia. By all accounts he handled his first military experience calmly and with dignity. Around the same time, the Imperial Family was fleeing revolutionary Vienna for the calmer setting of Innsbruck, in the Tyrol. Soon, the Archduke was called back from Italy, joining the rest of his family at Innsbruck by mid-June. It was at Innsbruck at this time that Franz Joseph first met his cousin Elisabeth, Duchess in Bavaria, his future bride, then a girl of ten, but apparently the meeting made little impact. Following victory over the Italians at Custoza in late July, the court felt safe to return to Vienna, and Franz Joseph travelled with them. But within a few months Vienna again appeared unsafe, and in September the court left again, this time for Olmütz in Moravia. By now, Prince Windischgrätz, the influential military commander in Bohemia, was determined to see the young Archduke soon put onto the throne. It was thought that a new ruler would not be bound by the oaths to respect constitutional government to which Ferdinand had been forced to agree, and that it was necessary to find a young, energetic emperor to replace the kindly, but mentally unfit Emperor. It was thus at Olmütz on 2 December that, by the abdication of his uncle Ferdinand and the renunciation of his father, the mild-mannered Franz Karl, Franz Joseph succeeded as Emperor of Austria. It was at this time that he first became known by his second as well as his first given name. The name "Franz Joseph" was chosen deliberately to bring back memories of the new Emperors great-grand-uncle, Emperor Joseph II, remembered as a modernizing reformer. Under the guidance of the new prime minister Prince Schwarzenberg, the new emperor at first pursued a cautious course, granting a constitution in early 1849. At the same time, military campaigns were necessary against the Hungarians, who had rebelled against Habsburg central authority under the name of their ancient liberties. Franz Joseph was also almost immediately faced with a renewal of the fighting in Italy, with King Charles Albert of Sardinia taking advantage of setbacks in Hungary to resume the war in March 1849. Soon, though, the military tide began to turn in favor of Franz Joseph and the Austrian whitecoats. Almost immediately, Charles Albert was decisively beaten by Radetzky at Novara, and forced both to sue for peace and to abdicate his throne. In Hungary, the situation was more grave and Austrian defeat was quite possible. Franz Joseph, sensing a need to secure his right to rule sought help from a reactionary Russia. With this Russian aid the Hungarian revolution was crushed by late summer of 1849. With order now restored throughout the Empire, Franz Joseph felt free to go back on the constitutional concessions he had made, especially as the Austrian parliament, meeting at Kremsier, had behaved, in the young Emperor's view, abominably. The 1849 constitution was suspended, and a policy of absolutist centralism was established, guided by the formerly liberal Minister of the Interior, Alexander Bach. The next few years saw the seeming recovery of Austria's position on the international scene following the near disasters of 1848–1849. Under Schwarzenberg's guidance, Austria was able to stymie Prussian scheming to create a new German Federation under Prussian leadership, excluding Austria. After Schwarzenberg's premature death in 1852, he could not be replaced by statesmen of equal stature, and the Emperor effectively took over himself as prime minister. On February 18, 1853, the Emperor survived an assassination attempt by Hungarian nationalist János Libényi. The emperor was taking a stroll with one of his officers Maximilian Karl Lamoral Graf O’Donnell von Tyrconnell on a city-bastion, when Libényi approached him. He immediately struck the emperor from behind with a knife straight at the neck. Franz Joseph almost always wore a uniform, which had a high collar that almost completely enclosed the neck. It so happened that the collar of his uniform was made out of very sturdy material. Even though the Emperor was wounded and bleeding, this collar basically saved his life. Count O'Donnell (descendant of the Irish noble dynasty O'Donnell of Tyrconnell[1] struck Libényi down with his sabre[1]. O'Donnell, hitherto only a Count by virtue of his Irish nobility, was therafter made a Count of the Habsburg Empire, conferred with the Commander's Cross of the Royal Order of Leopold, and his customary O'Donnell arms were augmented by the initials and shield of the ducal House of Austria, with additionally the double-headed eagle of the Empire. These arms are emblazoned on the portico of no. 2 Mirabel Platz in Salzburg, where O'Donnell built his residence thereafter. Another witness who happened to be nearby, the butcher Joseph Ettenreich, quickly overwhelmed Libényi. For his deed he was later elevated to nobility by the Emperor and became Joseph von Ettenreich. Libényi was subsequently put on trial and condemned to death for attempted regicide. He was executed on the Simmeringer Haide. After the unsuccessful attack the Emperor's brother Ferdinand Maximilian Joseph, the later Emperor of Mexico, called upon Europe's Royal families for donations to a new church on the site of the attack. The church was to be a Votivgabe (a thank-you present to God) for the rescue of the Emperor. It is located on Ringstraße in the district of Alsergrund close to the University of Vienna, and is known as the Votivkirche. Although in public life the Emperor was the unquestioned director of affairs, in his private life his formidable mother still had a crucial influence. Believing it necessary that the Emperor should soon marry and produce heirs, she hoped to match Franz Joseph with her sister Ludovika's eldest daughter, Helene ("Nené"), four years the Emperor's junior. However, instead, the Emperor became besotted with Nené's younger sister, Elisabeth ("Sisi"), a girl of sixteen, and insisted on marrying her instead. Sophie, despite some misgivings about her niece's appropriateness as an imperial consort, acquiesced, and in 1854 the young couple were married. Their married life was not happy: not only could Sisi never really adapt herself to the court and always had disagreements with the Royal Family, but their first daughter Sophie died as an infant, while the only son, Crown Prince Rudolf died, allegedly by suicide, in 1889 in the infamous Mayerling episode with his young mistress Baroness Mary Vetsera. The Empress herself was stabbed to death by an Italian anarchist in 1898; Franz Joseph never fully recovered from the loss. According to the future Empress-Consort Zita of Bourbon-Parma, he usually told his relatives "You'll never know how important she was for me." The 1850s witnessed several failures of Austrian external policy - the Crimean War and break-up with Russia, Austro-Sardinian War of 1859 against armies of the House of Savoy, and Napoleon III. The setbacks continued in the 1860s with Austro-Prussian War of 1866. It resulted in Austrian-Hungarian Dualism in 1867. Franz Joseph built a villa named Villa Schratt in Bad Ischl for his mistress, Katharina Schratt, an actress with whom he had a long-standing relationship which was, to a certain degree, tolerated by Sissi. In 1914 the heir to the throne, Archduke Franz Ferdinand, was assassinated in Sarajevo, leading to World War I. Emperor Franz Joseph died in 1916, aged 86, in the middle of the war. After the defeat in World War I, the Austro-Hungarian Monarchy dissolved into national states.</English>
		<French></French>
		<German>[H1]Franz Joseph I.[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Kaiser von Österreich, Apostolischer König von Ungarn und König von Böhmen[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lebenszeit: [\BOLD]1848-1916[PARAGRAPH:2:0]Franz Joseph I. (* 18. August 1830 in Wien-Schönbrunn; † 21. November 1916 ebenda) aus dem Haus Habsburg-Lothringen, war Kaiser von Österreich sowie Apostolischer König von Ungarn 1848–1916. Sein Name in den anderen Sprachen der Donaumonarchie: Francesco Giuseppe (italienisch), František Josef (tschechisch), I. Ferenc József (ungarisch), František Jozef I (slowakisch), Franciszek Józef (polnisch), Franjo Josip (kroatisch), Franc Jožef (slowenisch), Francisc Iosif (rumänisch), Franc Josyp I (ruthenisch/ukrainisch). Franz Joseph Karl von Habsburg wurde am 18. August 1830 um 9:45 Uhr als Sohn von Erzherzog Franz Karl, dem jüngeren Sohn von Kaiser Franz I., und Prinzessin Sophie von Bayern in Wien geboren. Nach der Niederschlagung der Märzrevolution und der anderen Revolutionen von 1848 waren große politische Veränderungen erforderlich, die Monarchie sollte ein neues Gesicht erhalten. Daher entsagte sein Onkel Ferdinand I., der aus Krankheitsgründen die Regierung einer Staatskonferenz überlassen hatte, am 2. Dezember 1848 dem Thron, den er andernfalls noch 27 Jahre innegehabt hätte. Erzherzog Franz Karl, Franz Josephs Vater, verzichtete, wie im Familienrat vereinbart, auf die Thronfolge. Franz Joseph I. wurde daher bereits mit 18 Jahren neuer Kaiser von Österreich. Von Anfang an sah er seine Hauptaufgabe darin, eine weitere Revolution zu verhindern, und stützte sich dabei hauptsächlich auf das Militär (Armee, Kriegsmarine) und die römisch-katholische Kirche. Kaum eine Darstellung zeigt ihn anders als in der Uniform des Obersten Kriegsherrn. Der stockkonservative „rothosige Leutnant“, wie er von Kritikern bezeichnet wurde, war in seinen ersten Regierungsjahren keineswegs beliebt. 1853 überlebte Franz Joseph ein Attentat und lernte in seiner Sommerresidenz in Ischl seine erst 16jährige Cousine Elisabeth kennen. Elisabeth war die zweite Tochter von Herzog Max Joseph in Bayern und Ludovika Wilhelmine, Tochter des bayerischen Königs Maximilian I. und Schwester von Franz Josephs Mutter Sophie. Eigentlich war zwischen den Müttern vereinbart, dass Elisabeths ältere Schwester Helene die Braut des 23-jährigen Franz Joseph I. werden sollte. Statt dessen verliebte sich Franz Joseph in Elisabeth, die er am 24. April 1854 in Wien heiratete. In der Folge stand der junge Kaiser, was sein Familienleben betraf, unter dem Einfluss seiner Gattin und seiner dominanten Mutter. In kurzer Zeit kamen drei Kinder zur Welt: Sophie (1855-1857), Gisela (1856-1932) und Kronprinz Rudolf (1858-1889). Franz Josephs Mutter wollte Elisabeth von der Erziehung ihrer ersten drei Kinder fernhalten; im daraus entstandenen Konflikt setzte sich Sisi durch. 1868 wurde ihr viertes Kind Marie-Valerie (1868-1924) geboren. 1866/1867 half Kaiserin Elisabeth Franz Joseph I. durch ihre sehr guten persönlichen Beziehungen zu Mitgliedern der ungarischen Hocharistokratie, den zur Befriedung der Monarchie dringend nötigen Ausgleich mit Ungarn zustande zu bringen. Hierauf wurde I. Ferenc Jozsef 1867 in Budapest feierlich zum König gekrönt. 1879 wurde die Silberhochzeit des Kaiserpaars mit dem vom Maler Hans Makart gestalteten Festzug über die Wiener Ringstraße gefeiert. Kaiser Franz Joseph hielt den Kronprinzen Rudolf von allen Staatsgeschäften fern. Nachdem Rudolf seine streng militärisch geprägte private Ausbildung - nach mehreren Interventionen seiner Mutter Elisabeth beim Kaiser - abbrechen durfte, widmete er sich naturwissenschaftlichen Studien und arbeitete an Brehms Tierleben mit. Er war auch als Journalist in der liberalen Presse tätig, natürlich anonym und ohne Wissen seines Vaters. Auf Druck des Kaisers heiratete er 1881 Prinzessin Stephanie, Tochter des belgischen Königs Leopold II.. Der Ehe entstammte eine Tochter, Elisabeth, geboren 1883. Kronprinz Rudolf starb am 30. Jänner/Januar 1889 durch Suizid. Das Recht der Thronfolge ging nach dem Tod Rudolfs und des Kaiserbruders Erzherzog Karl Ludwig im Jahre 1896 auf dessen Sohn und Franz Josephs Neffen, Erzherzog Franz Ferdinand über. Franz Josephs anderer Bruder, Maximilian, glückloser Kaiser von Mexiko), war dort 1867 erschossen worden. Franz Ferdinands Kinder waren jedoch nicht erbberechtigt, da er 1900 Gräfin Sophie Chotek (später von Franz Joseph zur Herzogin von Hohenberg erhöht) geheiratet hatte, die zwar dem tschechischen Uradel entstammte, aber dem Kaiserhaus nicht ebenbürtig war. Nach dem Tod ihres Sohnes Rudolf reiste Kaiserin Elisabeth ziel- und ruhelos in Europa umher. Am 10. September 1898 wurde sie in Genf von einem Attentäter, Luigi Lucheni, mit einer Feile ermordet. Das 60-Jahre-Jubiläum des Regierungsantritts Franz Josephs wurde im Jahre 1908 in Österreich gefeiert; in Wien fand - obwohl der Monarch davon nicht viel hielt - ein Kaiserjubiläumsfestzug auf der Ringstraße statt. Kaiser Wilhelm II. und sämtliche deutschen Monarchen besuchten Franz Joseph in Wien. Das offizielle Ungarn beteiligte sich nicht an den Feiern: Für die Ungarn war Franz Joseph erst seit seiner Krönung 1867 legitimer Monarch. Am 28. Juni 1914 erlebte der Kaiser den gewaltsamen Tod seines Thronfolgers Franz Ferdinand. In Sarajevo wurden der Thronfolger und seine Frau in ihrem Automobil von einem serbischen Attentäter erschossen. Franz Joseph zeigte wenig Mitgefühl und interpretierte den Doppelmord als „Wiederherstellung der höheren Ordnung“, die er selbst nicht habe schützen können; er meinte damit, dass er die morganatische Ehe seines Neffen nicht verhindern hatte können. Für einige österreichische (man sprach von der Wiener Kriegspartei) und ungarische Politiker war das Attentat aber der Anlass, den seit Jahren angestrebten Krieg gegen Serbien endlich auszulösen. Dem 84-jährigen Kaiser konnten sie einreden, dass der Tod seines ungeliebten Neffen die Ehre der Monarchie beschmutzt habe und sich Österreich-Ungarn gegen den kleinen, aber unberechenbaren Nachbarn wenden müsse. Das vom Kaiser genehmigte Ultimatum an das Königreich Serbien zur Auslieferung der Hintermänner des Attentats und die darauf folgende Kriegserklärung Österreich-Ungarns an Serbien lösten am 28. Juli 1914 den „großen Krieg” (später Erster Weltkrieg genannt) aus. Franz Joseph I. führte wegen seines hohen Alters den Oberbefehl über die k.u.k. bewaffnete Macht nicht selbst, sondern bestimmte Erzherzog Friedrich zum Armeeoberkommandanten. Zwei Jahre später verstarb der 86-jährige Franz Joseph I. mitten im Krieg am 21. November 1916. Die Begräbnisfeierlichkeiten waren der letzte große Auftritt der Donaumonarchie, die vom Kaiser zusammengehalten worden war. Sein Nachfolger Karl I. regierte nur noch zwei Jahre; 1918, am Ende des Weltkrieges, zerfiel die Monarchie. Die Literatur über Franz Joseph I. nennt zwei nichtadelige Frauen, zu denen der Kaiser intensive Beziehungen unterhalten hat: Anna Nahowski und Katharina Schratt.</German>
		<Italian></Italian>
		<Spanish></Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_FRANZ_1</Tag>
		<English>Greetings, [CT_NAME]! Would you like to drink a cup of coffee with me? Sissi, come on, lets bring us some coffee from the kitchen!</English>
		<French></French>
		<German>Servus, [CT_NAME]! Wolln's nit a bissl an Kaffee trinken? Geh, Sissi, hol an Kaffee aus da Küche!</German>
		<Italian></Italian>
		<Spanish></Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_REFUSE_TO_TALK_LEADER_FRANZ_1</Tag>
		<English>The Austrian people are not interested in your stories.</English>
		<French>Vos mots sont comme des tasses du feu pour les morts.</French>
		<German>Das österreichische Volk is nit an eure bleden Gschichtln intressiert.</German>
		<Italian>Le vostre parole sono come le tazze del fuoco per i morti.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Tus palabras son como las tazas del fuego para los muertos.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_NO_PEACE_LEADER_FRANZ_1</Tag>
		<English>Have you thought, you don't get your punishment, if you go to war with the [OUR_EMPIRE]?</English>
		<French>La guerre continuera, [OUR_EMPIRE] vous écrasera, [CT_NAME].</French>
		<German>Ja, habt's Ihr gedacht, Ihr kommt ungstraft davon, wenn euch mit dem [OUR_EMPIRE] anlegts?</German>
		<Italian>La guerra accenderà, [OUR_EMPIRE] li schiaccerà, [CT_NAME].</Italian>
		<Spanish>La guerra se encenderá, [OUR_EMPIRE] te machacará, [CT_NAME].</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FR_LEADER_FRANZ_1</Tag>
		<English>Sissi, please bring some coffee. Our good friend [CT_NAME] is here.</English>
		<French>C'est une occasion joyeuse toutes les fois que vous venez, [CT_NAME].</French>
		<German>Geh Sissi, bring bittschen an Kaffee. Unsa guter Freund [CT_NAME] is auf Besuch.</German>
		<Italian>È un'occasione joyous ogni volta che venite, [CT_NAME].</Italian>
		<Spanish>Es una ocasión feliz siempre que vengas, [CT_NAME].</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FUR_LEADER_FRANZ_1</Tag>
		<English>What do you want, [CT_NAME]? Don't expect to drink coffee with me and Sissi.</English>
		<French>De qu'avez-vous besoin ? Après tout, son sang est dans votre tête, [CT_NAME]</French>
		<German>Was wolln den Sie, [CT_NAME]? Erwartens nit, dass ma wir zwa und die Sissi jetzt an Kaffee trinken werdn.</German>
		<Italian>Di che cosa avete bisogno? Dopo tutto, la sua anima è in vostra testa, [CT_NAME]</Italian>
		<Spanish>¿Qué necesitas? Después de todo, su sangre está en tu cabeza, [CT_NAME]</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_WEAKER_FRANZ_1</Tag>
		<English>Also the brilliant Austrians have to help the poor countries sometimes.</English>
		<French>Même les civilisations faibles ont quelque chose à ajouter à mes quantités de richesse, [CT_NAME].</French>
		<German>Das brilliante österreichische Volk muss den kleinen Ländern ja auch amal unter die Arm greifen, gell?</German>
		<Italian>Anche le civilizzazioni deboli hanno qualcosa aggiungere alle mie quantità di ricchezza, [CT_NAME].</Italian>
		<Spanish>Incluso las civilizaciones débiles tienen algo agregar a mis cantidades de abundancia, [CT_NAME].</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_EQUAL_FRANZ_1</Tag>
		<English>My good colleague, we have the same strength! Give me what I want and I will guarantee that this will remain!</English>
		<French>Nous sommes en même position que je vois, ainsi satisfaisons, donnons l'aide à ceux qui a besoin de elle !</French>
		<German>Mein lieber Kolleg, wir sind derweil gleich stark! Damit des so bleibt, müssts Ihr ma an klanen Gfalln tun!</German>
		<Italian>Siamo nella stessa posizione che vedo, così soddisfiamo, diamo l'aiuto a coloro che lo ha bisogno!</Italian>
		<Spanish>¡Estamos en la misma posición que veo, tan satisfacemos, damos ayuda a las que la necesiten!</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_STRONGER_FRANZ_1</Tag>
		<English>Could you please give the little Austrian people something?</English>
		<French>Pourriez-vous svp épargner quelque chose pour la civilisation [OUR_CIV_ADJ] ?</French>
		<German>Könntets Ihr, mei reicher Freund, uns, dem klanen österreichischen Volk, nit a bissl behilflich sein?</German>
		<Italian>Potreste risparmiare prego qualcosa per la civilizzazione [OUR_CIV_ADJ]?</Italian>
		<Spanish>¿Podrías ahorrar por favor algo para la civilización [OUR_CIV_ADJ]?</Spanish>
	</TEXT>	
</Civ4GameText>